Population and Reproductive Health Oral History Project, 1971-2006
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Population and Reproductive Health Oral History Project oral histories
1971-2006
MS 406
60 boxes (28 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Forty-one interviews (with complete transcripts) of individuals throughout the world who have made important contributions to the reproductive health movement since 1965. Includes reproductive health advocates, communication specialists, lawyers, managers, physicians, researchers, social workers and others. The series addresses the historical period 1965-2005.
Project History
The Population and Reproductive Health Oral History Project began as a discussion in the Population, Reproductive Health, and Family Planning section of the American Public Health Association in the late 1990s. In her newsletter message to the section membership, Deborah R. McFarlane, then chair, discussed the need for archiving the papers of people in the field who were retiring and asked for ideas. Jack C. Smith, an eminent statistician at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), read the column and called Deborah. "Not only do the papers of prominent people in our field need to be saved," he said, "but we need to save their stories. These stories are far more compelling than statistics." Jack convinced Deborah and many others of the need to conduct an oral history project with leaders in the population and reproductive health movements.
Jack retired shortly after and spent the next several years looking for an appropriate repository, speaking with oral historians, professional organizations, and friends in the field. He secured funding for a pilot project interviewing the directors of the Division of Reproductive Health at CDC: these interviews were conducted by Rebecca Sharpless, director of the Institute for Oral History at Baylor University. Sadly, Jack died in October 2000, but not before he had identified the Sophia Smith Collection (SSC) at Smith College--following discussions with its director, Sherrill Redmon--as the best place to preserve the interviews and make them available for research. He was impressed with the commitment of the SSC to documenting the history of women's health and the reproductive rights movement and felt that the project's records would be a logical complement to the SSC's impressive holdings on the subject, including the Margaret Sanger Papers, the archives of Planned Parenthood Federation of America, and many other collections.
In 2001, the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation, in Menlo Park, California, generously awarded funding to Deborah R. McFarlane of the University of New Mexico for this project. Dr. J. Joseph Speidel, then population program director at Hewlett, has continued to assist the project with his connections to key figures throughout the field.
To preserve the accounts and papers of pioneers in population and reproductive health, McFarlane enlisted the support of the Sophia Smith Collection at Smith College and the Institute of Oral History at Baylor University. The thirty-eight interviews were conducted by Rebecca Sharpless and Deborah McFarlane between 2002 and 2005. The oral history tapes and transcripts arrived at the SSC beginning in 2005, where they were edited and processed by oral historian Revan Schendler.
Some of narrators in the Population and Reproductive Health Oral History Project have agreed to donate their papers to the SSC. Others will donate their papers to the Francis Countway Library of Medicine at Harvard University, or other appropriate archives. Where known, this information is included in the list of narrators.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Population and Reproductive Health Oral History Project, funded by the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation, includes accounts of individuals throughout the world who have made important contributions to the field. Reflecting the voices and perspectives of advocates, communication specialists, lawyers, managers, physicians, researchers, social workers and others, the series addresses the historical period 1965-2005.
There are forty-one audio recorded interviews with complete transcripts for each. Project records include correspondence and emails between project staff and narrators; and biographical materials, some of which include writings. Jack Smith's professional files include memoranda, emails, correspondence, newsletters, reports, database searches, and project proposals pertaining to the planning and execution of the History Project. They also document some of the important events in the history of the reproductive health movement since 1965. Also included are writings by Deborah McFarlane.
Selected transcripts have been digitized and are available on the SSC Web site.
Organization of the Collection
The collection is organized into three series:
I. ADMINISTRATIVE FILES AND PROJECT HISTORY
II. TRANSCRIPTS includes the full transcript (except where restricted sections have been removed), brief biographies, and notes.
III. BACKGROUND MATERIALS contains additional biographical information, research materials, correspondence and emails, notes, release forms, publications, annotated transcripts, audiotapes, and audio-only DVDs
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection except for the following interviews: Mohammed Alauddin, Peter J. Donaldson, Elizabeth Maguire, and Margaret Neuse. See box list below for specific closure periods.
Additional Formats
Audio recordings of interviews have been copied to CDRom for research use.
Transcripts are available in both paper and electronic formats.
Selected transcripts have been digitized and are available on the SSC Web site.
History of the Collection
Jack Smith donated his original project records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2000. Thirty-eight interviews were conducted by Rebecca Sharpless and Deborah McFarlane between 2002 and 2005, and Deborah McFarlane facilitated the transfer of the completed interviews and transcripts to the SSC from 2005-2007, where they were edited and processed by oral historian Revan Schendler.
Search Terms
Abortion--History--Sources; Birth control--History--Sources; Birth control--Law and legislation--History--Sources; Birth control--Research; Contraceptives--History; Oral histories; Population assistance--Developing countries; Reproductive health--History--Sources; Reproductive health--Developing countries; Pro-choice movement--History--Sources; National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion (U.S.). Division of Reproductive Health; International Conference on Population and Development (1994: Cairo, Egypt); Alan Guttmacher Institute; Catholics for a Free Choice (Organization); Centre for Development and Population Activities; International Planned Parenthood Federation; International Women's Health Coalition; Population Action International; United Nations Fund for Population Activities; USAID. Office of Population and Reproductive Health; Alauddin, Mohammad; Benshoof, Janet; Camp, Sharon; Cates, Willard; Concepcion, Mecedes; Curlin, Peggy; Darney, Philip D.; David, Henry P.; Delano, Grace Ebun; Donaldson, Peter J.; Duke, Robin Chandler Lynn; Dunlop, Joan; Frank, Richard; Germain, Adrienne; Gillespie, Duff; Gillespie, Robert; Jaramillo, Mario; Johnson, J. Timothy; Kabir, Sandra; Kissling, Frances, 1943-; Maguire, Elizabeth; Minto, Lee; Morris, Leo; Neuse, Margaret; Pellegrom, Daniel E.; Piotrow, Phyllis Tilson; Potts, Malcolm, 1935-; Ravenholt, Reimert T., 1925-; Richards, Cory L.; Rogers, Everett M.; Rosenfield, Allan; Rosoff, Jeannie Isabelle; Sadik, Nafis; Sai, Fred T.; Scruggs, Stirling; Seims, Sara; Sheeran, Patrick J.; Sinding, Steven W.; Speidel, J. Joseph (John Joseph), 1937-; Viravaidya, Mechai; McFarlane, Deborah R., 1951-; Sharpless, Rebecca; Smith, Jack, 1941-2000; Sophia Smith Collection
Additional Information
Related Material
Selected transcripts have been digitized and are available on the SSC Web site.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATIVE FILES AND PROJECT HISTORY
  - Jack Smith's administrative files: memoranda, emails, correspondence, newsletters, reports, database searches, and project proposals pertaining to the planning and execution of the initial phases of the project, 1971-2000 (Box 1)
  - Freeman, Ronald: curriculum vitae, and correspondence, 2004 (Box 2)
  - McFarlane, Deborah: writings and notes, 2001, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Smith, Jack: curriculum vitae, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Baylor University: original transcripts (unedited) on DVD, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Sophia Smith Collection project files, circa 2005-07 (Box 2)
- SERIES II. INTERVIEWS AND BACKGROUND MATERIALS
  - Alauddin, Mohammad (Box 3)
  - Benshoof, Janet (Box 4)
  - Camp, Sharon (Box 5)
  - Cates, Willard (Box 6)
  - Concepción, Mercedes (Box 7)
  - Curlin, Peggy (Box 8)
  - Darney, Philip (Box 9)
  - David, Henry P. (Box 10)
  - Delano, Grace Ebun (Box 11)
  - Donaldson, Peter J. (Box 12)
  - Duke, Robin Chandler (Box 13)
  - Dunlop, Joan (Box 14-15)
  - Frank, Richard (Box 16)
  - Germain, Adrienne (Box 17)
  - Gillespie, Duff (Box 18)
  - Gillespie, Robert (Box 19)
  - Jarmillo, Mario (Box 20-21)
  - Johnson, J. Timothy (Box 22)
  - Kabir, Sandra (Box 23)
  - Kissling, Frances (Box 24-26)
  - Maguire, Elizabeth (Box 27)
  - Minto, Lee (Box 28)
  - Morris, Leo (Box 29)
  - Neuse, Margaret [Closed until January 1, 2020] (Box 30)
  - Pellegrom, Daniel E. (Box 31)
  - Piotrow, Phyllis Tilson (Box 32)
  - Potts, Malcolm (Box 33)
  - Ravenholt, Reimert Thorolf (Box 34)
  - Richards, Cory L. (Box 35)
  - Rogers, Everett M. (Box 36)
  - Rosenfield, Allan (Box 37)
  - Rosoff, Jeannie Isabelle (Box 38)
  - Sadik, Nafis (Box 39)
  - Sai, Fred T. (Box 40)
  - Scruggs, Stirling (Box 41)
  - Seims, Sara (Box 42)
  - Sheeran, Patrick J. (Box 43)
  - Sinding, Steven (Box 44)
  - Speidel, J. Joseph (Box 45)
  - Viravaidya, Mechai (Box 46)
- SERIES III. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
  - Allaudin, Benshoof, Camp (Box 47)
  - Cates, Concepción, Curlin (Box 48)
  - Darney, David (Box 49)
  - Delano, Duke (Box 50)
  - Donaldson, Peter J. (Box 51)
  - Dunlop, Joan, [Digital file available] (Box 51)
  - Frank, Germain, Gillespie, D. (Box 52)
  - Gillespie, R., Jarmillo, Johnson (Box 53)
  - Kabir, Kissling, Maguire (Box 54)
  - Morris, Neuse, Pellegrom (Box 55)
  - Ravenholt (Box 56)
  - Piotrow, Richards (Box 57)
  - Rogers, Rosenfield, Rosoff, Sadik, Sai (Box 58)
  - Scruggs, Seims, Sheeran (Box 59)
  - Sinding, Speidel, Viravaidya, Minto (Box 60)